Ralph Russell Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Ralph Russell Papers.
undated, 1939-1977.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Russell, Ralph.
1 linear foot.
Ralph Russell was born in Nova Scotia in 1900. In 1902 Russell's family moved to Worcester, Massachusetts, where he was raised. Due to his political beliefs, as well as his activities on behalf of the United Public Workers Union, Russell found himself accused of being a member of the Communist Party. Despite a vigorous defense, Russell lost his position with the Bureau of Fisheries in 1953 and did not regain his job until 1958, when the Supreme Court ruled such termination unconstitutional. Russell remained with the Bureau until his retirement in 1965.
MSS19950009
Biography
Ralph Russell was born in Nova Scotia, Canada in 1900. In 1902 Russell's family moved to Worcester>, Massachusetts, where he was raised. Russell went on to obtain an education from the local public schools, the Massachusetts Agricultural College, and the University of Wisconsin, where he received a Masters Degree in rural Sociology. After a number of jobs, Russell secured a position with the Bureau of Fisheries within the Interior Department, in 1938. He eventually rose to the position of section chief.
Due to his political beliefs, as well as his activities on behalf of the United Public Workers Union, Russell found himself accused of being a member of the Communist Party. Despite a vigorous defense, Russell lost position with the Bureau of Fisheries in 1953 and did not regain his job until 1958, when the Supreme Court rules such termination unconstitutional. Russell remained with the Bureau until his retirement in 1965.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the Ralph Russell Papers span the years 1952-1958, though there is material from earlier and later years. The Russell Papers document his dismissal from and subsequent reinstatement in the Interior Department. Branded as a Communist conspirator during the height of the McCarthy era, the papers offer insight into the struggles of those Americans who were accused of being Communists and their efforts to retain employment.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal Files ( undated, 1939-1977 ) contains Russell's papers dealing with his dismissal. The series includes correspondence, transcripts from Loyalty Board hearings, Freedom of Information Act materials, and printed material.
Series II: Legal Files ( undated, 1949-1958 ) is comprised of the files of Harry C. Lamberton, Russell's lawyer. The series includes notes, correspondence, and printed materials.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to political activities and politicians. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Anti-communist movements--United States.; Discrimination in employment.; Blacklisting, Labor United States.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Publications.; Legal Records.; [Field notes.]
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Archives & Special Collections in 1995 and 1997.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Personal Files, undated, 1939-1977
  - Autobiographies, undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Citizenship, 1939-1948 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - FBI/CIA copies of correspondence, 1954-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Federal Register, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Freedom of Information Act request Interior, Department of, 1975-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - General, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Press release, 1953 October 13 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Security regulations, 1953 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Transcripts of proceedings, 1954 January 25 (Box 1:, Folder 10-11)
    - Transcripts of proceedings, 1954 January 26 (Box 1:, Folder 12-13)
  - “Loyalty Among Government Employees,” by Thomas Emerson and David Helfeld, 1948 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Loyalty Board, Interior Department: early, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Loyalty Board, Interior Department, 1948-1953 (Box 2:, Folder 16-19)
  - National Loyalty Board, 1951-1952 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - Notes, undated (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - Personal writings, undated (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - Security, 1952-1953 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
- Series II: Legal Files, undated, 1949-1961
  - General files, 1950-1961 (Box 3:, Folder 24-26)
  - Memoranda, 1953 (Box 3:, Folder 27)
  - Official correspondence, 1949-1958 (Box 3:, Folder 28-29)
  - Witnesses, undated (Box 3:, Folder 30)